Mss.B.P43 Mss.B.P43
American Philosophical Society
John Pershouse correspondence and papers, 1749-1899
Mss.B.P43
American Philosophical Society
5.0 volumes; 62 items.
This correspondence is principally concerned with business between Pershouse and his brother James in England, with comments on conditions and events in the United States, including anti-British feeling, Thomas Paine's return to America, Jefferson's administration, and immigration. The papers include Pershouse's journal (1800-1838), which includes accounts of travels in England, France, and the United States, letterbooks (1836-1862) of Henry Pershouse, nephew of John, chiefly on business matters, and two volumes of Pershouse genealogical data, compiled by B.M. Pershouse Bayley (1899).
5 volumes; 62 items.
Pershouse, John,1769-1841.
Box 1
Volume 5
Early American History Note
This collection contains five volumes of data relating to John Pershouse and his family. The collection contains two volumes of genealogical data from the later eighteenth century; the remaining three volumes all date to the early republic and consist of a travel journal and two letter books thought to belong to his nephew Henry. Of particular interest are the letters from Pershouse in Philadelphia to his brother in England. His letters often discuss many of the major political and social events happening in the early republic. He discusses immigration, Jefferson’s administration, and the culture of Philadelphia during this period.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased and accessioned, 1958 (1958 1433ms).
Existence and Location of Copies note
This material is also available on microfilm (Film 1370).
Biographical/Historical note
John Pershouse was a Philadelphia merchant.
Bayley, B. M. Pershouse; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809; Pershouse, Henry; Pershouse, James.; Business Records and Accounts; Diplomatic History; Early National Politics; England -- Description and travel.; Family Correspondence; Genealogies.; General Correspondence; International Travel; Journals (notebooks).; Letterbooks.; Philadelphia History; Political Correspondence; Social Life and Custom; Travel; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States -- Description and travel.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1809.
- Papers, 1794-1899
  Scope and Contents note
  D. 62 letters and documents and 5 ms. vols. Various sizes. Letters and documents are individually catalogued; 1794-1841. Vols.are: (John Pershouse. Journal; Feb. 1800-1838: B.M.P.Bayley. Genealogical data of the Pershouse family; 1899 and H. Pershouse. Letterbooks; 1836-1862.
  - Letter to James Pershouse, March 6, 1794; 9-3/4x7-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Manchester, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning the possible sale of land.
  - Letter to James Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, April 16, 1798; 8x7-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Nuremberg, A.L. 3p.and add.,end. Mutilated. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning his travels in Europe.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, May 5, 1801; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Ships flour. Concerning the price of provisions in England. Concerning Jefferson as president. Concerning political news in England. Concerning Pitt.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, June 30, 1801; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning the price of food in England and the need for care of land. Concerning his travels in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, Nov. 20, 1801; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning internal affairs in the U.S. Concerning English foreign affairs. Concerning vaccination in the U.S. Immigration to the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, Dec. 2, 1801; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Internal affairs and prosperity of the U.S. Value of land in England. Current events. Refers to Porcupine, Franklin and Paine. Business in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, England, Feb. 26, 1802; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Will stay longer in the U.S. Friendly advice on going into trade. Concerning congress and Jefferson. Refers to the Indians. Growth of cotton in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, England, June 14, 1802; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning some immigrants who return to England. State of commerce in the U.S. Hatred between North and South and fear that France, in Louisiana, will take the West, forecasts dissolution of the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, England, Sept. 20, 1802; 13x7-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    New York, A.L. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning his travels through New York state. Concerning T. Paine.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, Dec. 28, 1802; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning the French in Louisiana and Jefferson. Refers to Paine.
  - Letter to James Pershouse, Dec. 28, 1802; 9-3/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Copy. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. On same sheet as letter from John Pershouse to James Pershouse; Jan. 1, 1803.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, England, [1802]; 10-1/2x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters.. .) Concerning Paine and his coming to the U.S. Refers to Whitefield and Priestley. Business.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, Jan. 1, 1803; 9-3/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 3p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters.) Business. On same sheet is letter from John Pershouse to James Pershouse; Dec. 28, 1802.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, England, April 8, 1803; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,and.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning Louisiana and the West. Refers to Paine and Jefferson. Priestley given dinner by the APS.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, Lancashire, July 23, 1803; 13x7-3/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Swiss immigrantion to the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, England, Sept. 23, 1803; 9-3/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Germantown, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Yellow fever in Philadelphia. Business. Recommends he immigrate to the U.S. Concerning Jerome Bonaparte and T. Paine.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Dec. 15, 1803; 9x7-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Results of the yellow fever epidemic. Slaves in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Chorley, [1803]; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning internal improvements (roads and canals) of the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, England, Jan. 20, 1804; 9-1/2x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Revival of slave trade in the U.S. Current events. Refers to T. Jefferson. Jerome Bonaparte's marriage.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, May 4, 1804; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Praises the U.S. and urges him to immigrate. Refers to Jerome Bonaparte. Refers to Jefferson and Paine.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, England, Sept. 10, 1804; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Friendly letter. Concerning Jerome Bonaparte. Influx of immigrants. Will become a citizen. Refers to Priestley.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Sept. 24, 1804; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business.
  - Letter to Ja[me]s Pershouse, Stourbridge, March 10, 1805; 10-1/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning a trip in Pennsylvania. Refers to Priestley.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, May 25, 1805; 10-1/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1760-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Will stay in America. Concerning Paine.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Oct. 26, 1805; 10-1/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning T. Paine. Business. Concerning yellow fever. Current events.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Dec. 10, 1805; 10-1/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Jefferson's speech to congress. Refers to T. Paine.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Dec. 15, 1805; 10-1/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Rising feeling against impressment in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Feb. 23, 1806; 10-1/4x8-1/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. Contains pencilled note in German on add. sheet. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Sends gift of flour. Concerning T. Paine. Business. Growth of population in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, April 4, 1806; 10-1/2x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, June 18, 1806; 10-1/2x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning immigration to the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Oct. 24, Oct. 30, 1806; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Dec. 5, 1806; 13x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Refers to Jefferson. Concerning business in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, April 1, 1807; 10x7-3/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Friendly letter. Refers to an article in the Port Folio.
  - Letter to [James Pershouse], May 10, 1807; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Friendly letter. Concerning Thomas Paine.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Oct. 8, 1807; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add., end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning the Chesapeake and the Leopard affair. Refers to Jefferson. Concerning a comet.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Kingswinford, Feb. 5, 1808; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning Anglo-American relations.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, April 26, 1808; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning the Embargo.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Oct. 31, 1808; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Stourbridge, Dec. 3, 1808; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Concerning the Embargo.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, England, Nov. 11, 1809; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, England, June 10, 1810; 9-3/4x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Current events. Describes expanding economy of the U.S. Death of Paine. Business.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, Nov. 27, 1810; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Describes trip through Albany to Canada.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, England, Jan. 26, 1811; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and. add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Describes how a poor man may prosper in the U.S. Business. Concerning Dunkers. Concerning Indians of Canada.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, July 5, 1811; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning immigration to the U.S. Business. Describes a visit to Maryland. Current events.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, England, Dec. 12, 1811; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Development of manufactures in the U.S.
  - Letter to James Pershouse, Bridgenorth, March 17, 1812; 9x7-1/2; How and Marsham, Stock-Brokers
    London, Printed D.filled in in ms.and L. 2p. and add.,end. (See John Pershouse. Letters...) Business.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, England, June 2, 1812; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Possibility of war with Great Britain.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, England, Aug. 10, 1812; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning the war. Possible rise of manufactures in the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, Dec. 20, 1813; 10x8-1/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning the war. Concerning internal affairs of the U.S.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, June 17, 1815; 9-1/2x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning the peace and the development of the U.S. His plans to return to England.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, Aug. 14, 1815; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 4p.,add. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Business. Returns soon to England. Growth of the U.S. Return of Bonaparte.
  - Letter to [James] Pershouse, Bridgnorth, Dec. 30, 1815; 9x7-1/4; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    London, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Is in England and will visit him.
  - Letter to H[enry] Pershouse, Manchester, Nov. 2, 1817; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Pershouse, Elizabeth Pilling
    A.L.S. 3p. and add.with P.S. by J[ames] Pershouse. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Mrs. H. Pershouse, Manchester, Aug. 24, 1825; 9-1/4x7-1/2; Barlow, Elizabeth
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Friendly letter.
  - Policy issued to John Pershouse, May 20, 1826; 20-1/2x16-1/2; Protection Insurance Company
    Hartsford, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: T.C.Perkins, secy., Wm.W.Ellsworth, pres. and John Boardman, agent. 1p. (see John Pershouse. Letters...)
  - Passport issued to John Pershouse, Sept. 8, 1828; 16x12-3/4; Netherlands
    London, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: J.W.May. and John Pershouse. 1p.and end. In French. (see John Pershouse. Letters...)
  - Passport issued to John Pershouse, Aug. 28, 1829; 17x10-1/2; France
    London, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: John Pershouse. A. Billing,sec. 1p.and end. In French. (see John Pershouse. Letters.. .)
  - Ticket to Paris, July 20, 1830
    1 item, printed with Mss filled in. Ticket to Paris, issued by English and Foreign Coach Office.
  - Statement of property, March 1, 1833; 10x8; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    A.D. 4p. (see John Pershouse. Letters...)
  - Letter to R[obert] Ewing, June 4, 1841; 10x8; Bayard, James
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. Copy. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Advises mode of settling John Pershouse's estate. On same sheet as letter from R.Ewing to H.Pershouse; June 11, 1841.
  - Letter to Henry Pershouse, Manchester, June 11, 1841; 10x8; Ewing, Robert
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters.. .) Death of John Pershouse. Statement of John Pershouse's estate. Enclose copy of letter advising mode of settling the estate. On same sheet is copy of letter from J. Bayard to R. Ewing; June 4, 1841.
  - Letter to Henry Pershouse, Manchester, June 28, 1841; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Ewing, Robert
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see John Pershouse. Letters...) Concerning the settlement of John Pershouse's estate.
  - Analysis of the will of the late Henry Pershouse., [1862]
    A.D. 4p.
  - Decision concerning the will of James Taylor., Undated; 17x18; Catholic Church. Archdiocese of Canterbury (England)
    D.S.: Geo[rge] Goslling, Nath[anie]l Goslling and R.C.Cresswell, Deputy Registers. 1p. Stamped. Parchment. (see John Pershouse. Letter...)
  - Journal, Feb. 1800-1838; B P43.1; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Pershouse, John, 1769-1841
    A.D.S. 128p. of which 70 contain writing. End.: Henry Pershouse and G.H. Bradney Pershouse. Contains entries of his travels in the U.S.
  - Genealogical data of the Pershouse family, 1899; B P43.2; 7x4-1/2 and 8-3/4x7-1/4; Bayley, Benjamin M. Pershouse, 1864-
    A.D.S. 2 vols. Contains references to John and James Pershouse.
  - Letterbooks, 1834-1837; B P43.3; 11x9, 12-3/4x8; Pershouse, Henry, 1799-1862
    A.L.S. 2 volumes. Vol. 1 contains comments on books which he read, dated: 1834-1837. Vol. 2 contains entry on death of John Pershouse. Letters are mostly business letters.